Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1. 2013 accrual: End of the Line and Finest Kind files, March 1, 2010 through March 30, 2010, June 28 2010 through July 30 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 822 TIFF, 2 jpg, 2 pdf, 2 xls, and 1 docx
  - Subseries 2. Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine files, June 28 2010 through July 30 2010, 488 TIFF, 1 pdf, 1 xls
    The digital files on disk have not been rearranged from their original order. The manuscript files have been described in alphabetical order in the finding aid and the photographs are listed in numerical order by ID number. The photographs' titles and ID numbers are copied from Starr's item level metadata in his descriptive spreadsheet "manifest_ph0337-ph0824_inventory.xls". The descriptions and listings of individuals in the photos are used as titles. If a description was too long to be an effective title archivists shortened it and recorded the original description in the item's Scope and Content note. The dates come from the photographs' EXIF metadata, except where that data is clearly inaccurate. In those cases archivists estimated an accurate date. See the inventory and files' metadata for more context.
    - Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 pdf
    - Photo inventory, July 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 xls
    - Two lobstermen paddle their skiff home past docks stacked with gear in Prospect Harbor, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Two lobstermen paddle their skiff home past docks stacked with gear in Prospect Harbor. This standing and paddling method used to propel skiffs is the standard in the harbor.
    - Two fiberglass lobsterboats at anchor at end of day, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Two fiberglass lobsterboats at anchor at end of day. Nearly all boats in the harbor are glass, although there are a few wooden boats left. Boat on left is Arvid Young's boat, of Young's Boatbuilders fame.
    - Boats at rest in front of Corea Fishermen's Coop, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Boats at rest in front of Corea Fishermen's Coop. All but a few boats in the harbor belong to the coop. Lobstermen get bait, fuel and supplies from the coop and drop off their catch at the end of the day. Hired workers at the coop box and sell the catch for them.
    - Virgo heads up into Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Virgo heads up into Gouldsboro Bay. Just above Corea's harbor, this bay is nearly 7 miles deep and nearly all of the Corea fishermen set traps in the bay (note the number of buoys in the photo - the whole bay is covered with them) although most of the fishermen also fish out in the open ocean, depending on the movement of the lobsters. Lobsters travel on or offshore depending on water temperatures. Doubles, primarily, are fished in the bay, along with singles, due to the crowded conditions. Longer trawls, of anywhere from 5 to 30 traps are fished offshore to save time where entanglements are less likely.
    - Gulls sitting on wire traps, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Gulls sitting on wire traps. Gear encircles Corea harbor in the off season.
    - Two boats heading out of Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Two lobstermen paddle out to the Pamela Ann for a day's work, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Two lobstermen paddle out to the Pamela Ann for a day's work. The man on the right is the oldest man fishing in Corea - 80 years old at the time of the photo. Brandon Sprague left, Babe Crowley right
    - Two lobstermen paddle home at the end of the day's work. Ethan Whittaker left, Brandon Johnson right, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Two lobstermen load bait for the next day's fishing, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Two lobstermen load bait for the next day's fishing. Herring is the preferred bait in Corea, but alewives are used when they run upstream in local waters in the spring.
    - Lobstermen's wharfs are used to store gear and as a place from which to load their vessels with equipment. They can also tie their vessels to the piers and wait for low tide to inspect the bottoms of their boats or make repairs, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Lobstermen's wharfs are used to store gear and as a place from which to load their vessels with equipment. They can also tie their vessels to the piers and wait for low tide to inspect the bottoms of their boats or make repairs. The shacks on the dock originally were used in the winters as workshops, where they could make wooden traps and buoys (no longer used anywhere) or maintain other gear. Lobstermen now mostly work on gear in other locations. Note the lobster car in the foreground loaded with spare traps. As not all fishermen have wharfs, sometimes gear is stored on the water. Cars are used to store lobsters until needed for sale - floating crates that can double as docks.
    - Tools of the trade. A lobster gauge on top measures both the short and long legal limits, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Tools of the trade. A lobster gauge on top measures both the short and long legal limits. At the time of the photos, lobsters had to measure at least 3.25" and no longer than 5." along the carapace. The device on the bottom is a bander - used to stretch the rubber bands around the claws of lobsters they were going to keep - this protected the fishermen from claws while also keeping the lobsters from tearing each other apart. Both tools are made from stainless steel.
    - Virgo in Gouldsboro Bay. Captain is about to launch a trap back into the water, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Three vessels await their turn to unload at the Coop, July 23, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Three vessels await their turn to unload at the Coop. The Coop can only handle two boats at a time, so vessels idle in the mouth of the harbor until a spot opens up on the docks. Boats leave from the harbor anywhere from 4AM to 7Am and begin to return in the early afternoon.
    - Boats in the harbor at the end of the day, July 24, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Boats in the harbor at the end of the day. Note the stony nature of the harbor shoreline.
    - Skiffs tied to the dock, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Skiffs tied to the dock. Many of the skiffs in the harbor are home-made by the fishermen, although there are also commercial skiffs in use. Only one or two have outboards on them - an unnecessary expense and an additional maintenance problem they don't need.
    - More skiffs. Fishermen paddle their skiff out to the boat and leave it on the boat's mooring until they return at the end of the day, July 24, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Low tide and skiffs, July 24, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Fish ladder to the pond on the Guzzle Road. In the spring, a trap is set here for alewives that head into the pond to spawn, July 25, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Fish ladder to the pond on the Guzzle Road. In the spring, a trap is set here for alewives that head into the pond to spawn. Fishermen buy the rights to the fish at a town auction each year - promising to pay so much per bushel of fish. This bait is then sold to others in Corea. Ethan Whitaker owned the rights at the time of the photo, and he lives just up the street, as does his father.
    - Mushroom anchor and buoy exposed at low tide in Corea Harbor, July 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Trap coming aboard onto the sidedeck. This is the tail trap of a double trawl, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Trap coming aboard onto the sidedeck. This is the tail trap of a double trawl. It will be slid aft to the sternman and the captain will deal with the head trap that comes aboard next.
    - Arvid Young aboard Tenaru River (named for the famous battle of WWII), July 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Arvid Young aboard Tenaru River (named for the famous battle of WWII). One of three brothers that ran Young Brother's Boatbuilding Co. in Corea (out of business at time of photo.) The Youngs were some of the original settlers in the area.
    - Boat at the Coop dock unloading lobsters, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Boat at the Coop dock unloading lobsters. Kevin on the left weighs lobsters from the boat and will make out a slip with the final number of pounds landed. Bruce Hartford on the boat has another tote of lobsters to land. The traps on the boat were picked up during the day and will be moved to another location ahead of the lobster's migration. Docks are actually lobster cars as well. Kevin Scully left, Bruce Hartford right
    - Brandon Sprague and Babe Crowley head to the next string of traps on the Pamela Ann. Brandon Sprague left, Babe Crowley right, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Babe Crowley and Brandon Sprague empty and rebait a pair of traps on the bay. Babe (Harold) Crowley left, Brandon Sprague right, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Babe Crowley grabs a buoy with a boothook, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Babe Crowley grabs a buoy with a boothook. The boat runs up on a buoy so that the captain can grab the buoys and then feed the line through the block and into the pot hauler. Sea urchins line the deck and rails. Unwanted guests, the urchins can fully pack the trap and keep lobsters out. They are sometimes crushed or simply dumped back overboard, and cost much time and effort. There is a winter business in sea urchin harvesting in Corea. Divers collect the urchins and they are sent to Japan for consumption.
    - Babe Crowley at work on the Pamela Ann, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Babe Crowley crushes sea urchins with a hammer. They can fill the trap and prevent lobsters from entering the trap, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Harold "Babe" Crowley at 80 years of age, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Harold "Babe" Crowley at 80 years of age. Perhaps the most respected fisherman in the village, and the oldest person fishing from the harbor
    - Harold "Babe" Crowley, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Harold "Babe" Crowley. Crowleys were some of the first settlers in the area.
    - Harold "Babe" Crowley, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Harold "Babe" Crowley at the coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Harold "Babe" Crowley steering the Pamela Ann, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon Sprague waiting for the traps to break the surface of the water aboard the Pamela Ann, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon Sprague and Babe Crowley unloading a tote of lobsters at the Coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Brandon Sprague and Babe Crowley unloading a tote of lobsters at the Coop. The totes were loaded with 90 pounds of lobsters. Kevin Scully, a worker at the coop stands on the dock. He will weigh the lobsters and give Babe a receipt for the total pounds landed, as well as for any bait, fuel or other supplies taken aboard. Brandon Sprague left, Babe Crowley right Kevin Scully on dock.
    - Brandon Sprague looks out at the rising sun on his commute to work on Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon Sprague banding lobsters on Pamela Ann, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon Sprague banding lobsters on Pamela Ann, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon Sprague emptying a trap of lobsters, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Babe and Brandon empty traps of lobsters, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Babe and Brandon empty traps of lobsters. Lobsters that are obviously too short or long are tossed back overboard. The rest will be placed in the compartments in the table in the foreground to be measured with gauges when time allows. If they are the right size, they will be banded and put into tanks with circulating water.
    - Calypso heads out to Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Calypso heads out to Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Calypso hauling traps outside of Gouldsboro bay, July 27, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Bait bags ready for use, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Bait bags ready for use. The sternmen on lobster boats pre-load baitbags to keep things moving once the boat gets to the traps. Traps are hauled, emptied, baited and relaunched within minutes. These bags are filled with herring, although when these photos were taken, fishermen were also using pogies, which they did not like. Getting bait and the cost of bait were a real problem for Corea fishermen in the summer of 2010
    - Bait bags ready for use, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Banding lobsters at the table, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Banding lobsters at the table. Rubber bands are stretched by the plier-like banding tool and protect both the fishermen and other lobsters from the powerful claws.
    - A cormorant fishing in the bay, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - A "berried" female lobster, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      A "berried" female lobster. Tens of thousands of lobster eggs are glued to the tail of this female. Egg bearing females are thrown back overboard, as they represent the future of fishing. They can also be v-notched. A v-cut notch in the tail marks the bearing female even if she has no eggs, and no lobster with a v-notch can be landed. This has assured a continuing crop of lobsters for Maine fishermen.
    - Low tide, July 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Low tide. The tidal range in Corea Harbor keeps fishermen from simply tying their boats to their wharves. Lobster boats are moored on fixed anchors because of this. Note in this mid-day photo that most of the fleet is out working.
    - Low tide, July 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Low tide. The tidal range in Corea Harbor keeps fishermen from simply tying their boats to their wharves. Lobster boats are moored on fixed anchors because of this.
    - Leigh Farnsworth unloading her catch at the coop, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Leigh Farnsworth unloading her catch at the coop. At the time of these photos, she was one of two women captains in the harbor. There were many women working as sternmen (they prefer to be called sternmen rather than sternwomen, fishermen over fisherwoman). Mostly they avoid the semantic gender problem by saying they fish or they stern on a lobster boat. Corea has a long history of women in the industry - wives often helped husbands on their boats in the past. Today, there are many husband/wife teams working from the harbor.
    - Hauling block that leads the line from the trap to the automatic pot-hauler, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Hauling block that leads the line from the trap to the automatic pot-hauler. These blocks, from Tenant's Harbor, seem to be the block used throughout the industry in New England.
    - Jewels and Virgo at work on Gouldsboro Bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Jewels and Virgo at work on Gouldsboro Bay. Covered with thousands of buoys, boats often work in close proximity on the bay.
    - A hauling block and another boat passing by on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - A lobster boat passes by on a foggy day off the coast, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Virgo steaming to the beginning of the next string of traps, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Virgo and Jewels working on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Two fishermen paddle their skiff to the boat to begin the days work, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - View through hauling block davit with lobsterboat in the distance, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boat at the Coop dock unloading lobsters. Kevin Scully on the dock, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Buoys and boat in the fog on the bay, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, June 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boats on their moorings in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Thai Baby returns home from an offshore trip, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Thai Baby returns home from an offshore trip. Bob Anderson, who owns the boat, named it in honor of his Thai wife. He prefers to fish way off-shore and so leaves very early and returns very late in the day.
    - Bow of Bottom Line at anchor in harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Line of boats moored in harbor, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day. These trawls have been moved from the head of Gouldsboro Bay where they had stopped catching lobsters and hopefully, into position to catch other lobsters moving out. Brandon Johnson was the sternman for Ethan Whittaker.
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      New trawls are set offshore early morning on a rough day. These trawls have been moved from the head of Gouldsboro Bay where they had stopped catching lobsters and hopefully, into position to catch other lobsters moving out. At this point, the whole set of traps nearly went overboard in the rough seas, and Brandon is trying to keep that from happening. (They didn't lose any.)
    - Brandon removes lobsters from the trap, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon removes lobsters from the trap, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon removes lobsters from the trap. Lobsters that are too short or too big are tossed back overboard, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Brandon removes lobsters from the trap, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Gauging a lobster to make sure it is of legal size, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Gauging a lobster to make sure it is of legal size. Bait in foreground is herring.
    - Brandon waiting to launch traps that are being moved to a new location, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Five boats from Corea work traps outside of the harbor on a bright day, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Five boats from Corea work traps outside of the harbor on a bright day. Most fishermen from the port have traps in Gouldsboro Bay as well as in waters offshore. Some travel up to 25 mile offshore to set traps throughout the year.
    - Skiffs in Corea Harbor, July 18, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Britt -E at work in the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - The sternman on Brown Eyed Girl dumps old bait overboard as they head out of the harbor for the day's work, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Buckets of herring on the coop dock, July 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Buckets of herring on the coop dock. The coop sells bait by the bucket or by the tote, each measured in bushels.
    - Lobsters banded and ready to bring back to port, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Lobsters banded and ready to bring back to port. Corea, at the time of these photos, was landing about a million pounds of lobsters a year.
    - Bell buoy outside of Corea Harbor, July 27, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Bell buoy outside of Corea Harbor. Rocking motion would cause clappers on buoy to strike bell and help guide fishermen home in the fog. Of course when these images were taken, gps technology had replaced this older device...
    - Foam buoys, June 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Foam buoys. Many of the elder fishermen talked of the days when they carved their buoys from cedar trees. The wooden buoys would have to be swapped out during the summer as they became waterlogged. Buoys are painted with the official colors assigned to each lobsterman, and one example of their buoy is prominently displayed on their vessel.
    - A snarl of buoys in the harbor caused by a storm, June 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casenty sinks into a trough while tending her traps, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - A boat heads out of Gouldsboro Bay - they are moving traps to a new location, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Walter Moore Jr. at the coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Walter Moore Jr. at the coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Walter Moore Jr. unloading lobsters at the coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Walter Moore Jr. unloading lobsters at the coop, July 26, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - The Captain Brennon and Empty Pockets at work on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - The Captain Brennon at work on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - The Captain Brennon at anchor in the harbor, July 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Boat at work on the ocean, July 19, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casenty heads out in the early morning from the harbor, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casenty heads out in the early morning from the harbor, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cassenty heads out in the early morning from the harbor, July 21, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya hauling traps on the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Casey*N*Taya running in the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Christine A hauled and placed next to owner's garage, July 20, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Christine A hauled and placed next to owner's garage. Corea's fleet is hauled for winter by a hydraulic trailer and the boats are often stored for a few months in the owner's yard. In some cases, when the owner has died, the boat is hauled and brought home in the summer. There are a handful of boats in the harbor that fish all winter and are not hauled at all.
    - Cindy Lee running in the ocean, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cindy Lee running in the ocean, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cindy Lee running in the ocean, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cindy Lee running into the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cindy Lee working her traps in the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cindy Lee working her traps in the bay, July 22, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF